Helen Begley Nixon Papers, 1945-1951
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Helen Begley Nixon papers
1945-1951
Nixon, Helen Begley, 1900-1990
MS 113
4 boxes (1.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Red Cross official; Relief worker, World War II; Refugee relief organizer, Vietnam; and President, International Women's Association, Vietnam. The papers document the lives of women in Korea; in Germany after World War II; and in Vietnam, as well as orphanages, and refugees. Material includes correspondence, photographs, and memorabilia; approximately one quarter of the collection is in German, and some is in Vietnamese, Korean, and French.
Helen Begley Nixon was born on March 13, 1900, in Holyoke, Massachusetts, daughter of Mr. and Mrs Thomas E. Begley. She graduated from Holyoke High School in 1917. Following graduation from Smith College in 1921, she taught English and history at the Allegheny County Academy in Cumberland, Maryland for five years. Between 1926 and 1948 she was director of the Red Cross in Holyoke, and Red Cross civilian relief representative in the American military governments of France, Belgium, Austria, and Germany. From 1946 to 1948 she was Chief Advisor of the Women's Bureau of the American military government in Korea where she helped reestablish the Korean Red Cross. From 1948 to 1953 Nixon was Cultural Officer for the Public Affairs Division of Women's Affairs for the U.S. High Commissioner in Germany, Cecil Lyon. She administered adult education and community organizing. Beginning circa 1955 to 1957, Nixon was the Refugee Settlement Advisor of the International Cooperation Administration Mission. the U.S. Great Britain, and France, plus seven voluntary agencies (CARE, Church World Service, Catholic Relief Services, International Research Council) who gave money, food, clothing, farm tools, and drugs to Vietnam. Her job was to resettle 650,000 refugees. She also established the first International Women's Association in Vietnam and served as it's first president. She also served on the Board of the Family Welfare School for Young Women. In 1957 she returned to the United States, and circa 1961 became an agency social worker with the Jicarilla Tribe in Dulce, New Mexico.
The Helen Begley Nixon papers consist of 1.5 linear feet (4 document boxes) of correspondence, photographs, printed material, and memorabilia reflecting her professional life. In addition there is material she collected on subjects that were of interest to her, mostly about women. The Papers are arranged in three series (I. Korea, II. Germany, and III. Vietnam) by country in general chronological order. Approximately one quarter to one third of the material is in German, and an additional quarter in Vietnamese, Korean, and French. There is virtually no personal material.
The smallest amount of material is from Nixon's time in Korea and consists of four folders. These contain printed material and reports about women in Korea, reports, and one photograph of the General Federation of Korean Women, plus correspondence and printed material from the Women's Bureau of the Office of the Military Governor, 1946-55. In this series there is also a folder of printed material about women in China and Japan that Nixon obviously collected while in Korea.
The largest portion of the Nixon papers is from Germany, most of which is contained in 10 linear inches of reports and related material (1945-53) collected while Nixon was associated with the Women's Affairs Branch of the U.S. High Commission for Occupied Germany. These cover a wide range of topics, including, education and culture, exchanges with women in the United States, women's organizations, employment and the position of women in Germany after World War II. Included also in this series is general printed material (clippings, articles, periodicals) about women in Germany, plus one photograph (1952) of Dr. Dorothy Fosdick and Dr. Else Ulich-Beil President of Deutscher.
The final series is from Vietnam and reflects Nixon's role as Refugee Settlement Advisor of the International Cooperation Administration in Vietnam. This consists of five inches of material, including articles, clippings and printed material about women in Vietnam, 1954-1957; reports, memos and correspondence about orphanages, International Women's Association, refugees and voluntary agencies. This series also contains 27 photographs.
This collection is organized into three series:
I. Korea
II. Germany
III. Vietnam
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The Papers are open to research without restriction according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any added restrictions.
History of the Collection
The Helen Begley Nixon Papers were a gift of Mrs. Nixon, 1966-1972.
Search Terms
Nixon, Helen Begley, 1900-1990; International Women's Association--Vietnam--History; Korea--Social conditions--1945- --Sources; Refugees--Vietnam--Sources; United States. Office of High Commissioner for Germany. Women's Affairs Branch--Sources; Vietnam--Social conditions--20th century--Sources; Women--Germany--History--20th century--Sources; Women--International cooperation--History--Sources; Women--Korea--History--20th century--Sources; Women--Vietnam--History--20th century--Sources; World War, 1939-1945--Civilian relief--Europe--Sources; World War, 1939-1945--War work--Red Cross--Sources; World War, 1939-1945--Women--Sources
- Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Biographical information (Box 1)
- SERIES I. KOREA
  - Clippings, articles, and printed material, 1945-53 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General Federation of Korean Women's Clubs: correspondence, printed material, and photograph, 1947-53 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Women's Bureau: correspondence and printed material, 1946-55 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - China and Japan: correspondence, miscellaneous printed material (collected by Nixon while in Korea), 1949-52 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- SERIES II. GERMANY
  - Reports and memos, 1945-52 (Box 2, Folder 6-10)
  - Reports and memos, 1953, undated (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
  - Printed material
    - Buro zum Studiem der U.S.A., 1950-51 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - The Bulletin, A Weekly Survey of German Affairs, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Der Staatsburgen, 1953-61 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous articles, pamphlets and printed material, 1947-64 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1949-61 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Photograph of Dr. Dorothy Fosdick and Dr. Else Ulich-Beil, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- SERIES III. VIETNAM
  - Clippings, articles and printed material, 1954-57 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Orphanages: Reports, memos and correspondence, 1955-56 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - International Women's Association: Reports, memos and correspondence, 1956-57 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Refugees: Reports, 1954-57 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Education: Reports, 1955, n.d (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Voluntary Agencies Coordinating Committee: Reports, 1954-56 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Photographs
    - Meeting of the International Women's Association at the Palace with Mme Ngo-dinh-Nhu as hostess (22 photos) (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Nixon with Milo Kamstra of CARE (2) (Box 4)
    - CARE package distribution (2) (Box 4)
    - Nixon alone (1) (Box 4)